<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>programmerraja blog</title>
    <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on programmerraja blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Philosophy of Software Design Book Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/a-philosophy-of-software-design-book-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/a-philosophy-of-software-design-book-notes/</guid>
      
      <description>The Nature of Complexity Complexity is anything related to the structure of a software systemthat makes it hard to understand and modify the system.
Symptoms of complexity Change amplification: The first symptom of complexity is that a seemingly simple change requires code modifications in many different places. Cognitive load: how much a developer needs to know in order to complete a task Unknown unknowns: it is not obvious which pieces of code must be modified to complete a task, or whatinformation a developer must have to carry out the task successfully Strategic vs.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android internal Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/android-internal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/android-internal/</guid>
      
      <description>File system Android devices typically have a partitioned storage system, where the storage is divided into different partitions, each serving a specific purpose.
/system: This directory contains the Android operating system and system applications. It is read-only to ensure the integrity of the system. Modifying files in this directory could potentially harm the device.
/app: prebundled apps from Google, as well as any vendor or carrier-installed apps /bin: various daemons, as well as shell commands contain bootanimation,dalvikvm, adb, etc.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/linux-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/linux-notes/</guid>
      
      <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wireshark Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/wireshark/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/wireshark/</guid>
      
      <description>Wireshark
help -&amp;gt; content have doc for all feature Analysis TCP
Stream index : calculate by wireshark to keep track of stream Sequence number Will show relative sequence number 1,2 to see the original right click -&amp;gt; protocol prefrences -&amp;gt; uncheck relative sequence number. flags ack,reset,etc. window size value calculated window size -&amp;gt; host window size checksum : wireshark not validate the check if we want ight click -&amp;gt; protocol prefrences -&amp;gt; check validate TCP check sum ifpossible options max segement size</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/docker/</guid>
      
      <description>Docker Engine When you install Docker, you get two major components:
Docker client →is a command-line tool used to interact with the Docker Engine, Docker daemon (sometimes called “server” or “engine”) In a default Linux installation, the client talks to the daemon via a local IPC/Unix socket at /var/run/docker.sock The Docker engine is the core software that runs and manages containers.The Docker Engine is made from many specialized tools that work together to create and run containers APIs, execution driver, runtime (create containers) , shims, containerd (to manage container lifecycle operations — start | stop | pause | rm.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Database internal book Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/database-internal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/database-internal/</guid>
      
      <description>Storage Engines The storage engine (or database engine) is a software component of a database man‐ agement system responsible for storing, retrieving, and managing data in memory and on disk, designed to capture a persistent, long-term memory of each node.
Storage engines such as BerkeleyDB, LevelDB and its descendant RocksDB, LMDB and its descendant libmdbx, Sophia, HaloDB,
Row-Oriented Data Layout Row-oriented database management systems store data in records or rows. Their layout is quite close to the tabular data representation, where every row has the same set of fields.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MicroServices</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/microservices/</guid>
      
      <description>Questions to be asked
How will new service be deployed and upgraded how will it be consumed by the rest of the system Service Mesh envoy,istio
API gateway
AWS API TAG (Tinder API Gateway) Krakend to learn
how to get more follower tiwtter / linkdein </description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Networking Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/networking/</guid>
      
      <description>OSI Model The Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) model describes seven layers that computer systems use to communicate over a network.
Application Layer (Htttp,DHCP,FMTP,Telnet,NFS) Presentation Layer (Encryption,Data format,Data compression,ASCII to Bin) Session Layer (TCP/IP socket authentication RTCP protocol) Transport Layer (Process level addressing TCP/UDP, Multiplexing,demultiplexing,segmentation,connection establishment) Network Layer (logical addressing IP , Routing, packet encapsulation) Data Link Layer (LAN,MAC,Data framing,Error detection) Physical Layer (Converting Bin to singals to transfer the data) Application Layer HTTP/HTTPS Is the protocol used to communicate with server.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NPM source code</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/npm-source-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/npm-source-code/</guid>
      
      <description>The arborist manages three trees:
actual virtual ideal The actual tree is what&amp;rsquo;s present on disk in the node_modules tree</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture and Decision-Making</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/software-architecture-and-decision-making/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/software-architecture-and-decision-making/</guid>
      
      <description>Books for leadership The Hard Things About Hard Things by Ben Horowitz, Trillion Dollar Coach by Eric Schmidt et al., Team of Teams: New Rules of Engagement for a Complex World by Stanley McChrystal, Good Strategy, Bad Strategy by Richard Rumel</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech stack of popular companies</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/tech-stack-of-popular-companies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/tech-stack-of-popular-companies/</guid>
      
      <description>Shopify’s Back-end: Ruby on Rails (+ some Lua and Go) Datastores MySQL , Redis for queues and background jobs Front-end: React with GraphQL API Type : monolith architecture: domain-driven, Multi-Tenant Architecture load balancing layer : Nginx, Lua, and OpenResty. Tinder 500 microservice Linkedin Azure front end for CDN Cloudfare Logging : ELK and Clickhouse </description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nginx Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/nginx/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/nginx/</guid>
      
      <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/go/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 11:39:28 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/go/</guid>
      
      <description>Introduction From c++ by google c++ author will convert to exe
go get githublink→ to download pkg and put under folder pkg
it has main function to run go run filename.go
package main //-&amp;gt; our package name imort &amp;#34;fmt&amp;#34; import (&amp;#34;fmt&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;math&amp;#34;) //-&amp;gt; to import multiple pkg func main(){ fmt.Println(&amp;#34;hello&amp;#34;) } Data types string, bool, int, byte , float32 ,float64, arrays
using var keyword and const → to not reassign
var name string = “d” (if directly assing vaule we don’t need to mention the data type)</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/kubernetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/kubernetes/</guid>
      
      <description>Kubernetes is two things A cluster for running applications An orchestrator of cloud-native microservices apps Kubernetes cluster A Kubernetes cluster contains six main components:
API server: Exposes a REST interface to all Kubernetes resources. Serves as the front end of the Kubernetes control plane. Scheduler: Places containers according to resource requirements and metrics. Makes note of Pods with no assigned node, and selects nodes for them to run on. Controller manager: Runs controller processes and reconciles the cluster’s actual state with its desired specifications.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning from blog</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/learning-from-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 08:19:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/learning-from-blog/</guid>
      
      <description>How LinkedIn Adopted Protocol Buffers to Reduce Latency by 60% They heavly using microservice to avoid the latency between the service they go with protocol buffers Protocol buffer (Protobuf) is a data serialization format and a set of tools to exchange data. Protobuf keeps data and the metadata separate. And serializes data into binary format. Use Protobuf when: Payload is big Communication between non-JavaScript environments needed Frequent changes to the payload schema expected Scaling Slack’s Job Queue They using redis queue for all async operation they have face few issue with that such as Operational Memory Constraints in Redis, Complex Redis Connection Structure ,Worker Scalability Dependency on Redis etc Instead fully replace with kafa they go step by step.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RabbitMQ Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2023/rabbitmq/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 18:26:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2023/rabbitmq/</guid>
      
      <description>What is RabbitMQ? RabbitMQ is a popular open-source message broker that implements the AMQP (Advanced Message Queuing Protocol) standard.
Channel A channel is a separate communication channel within a single connection. Channels allow multiple concurrent exchanges to be executed in parallel, providing a way to separate different parts of your application.
Each channel has its own set of resources, such as queues, exchanges, and bindings, which are independent of the resources used by other channels in the same connection.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello world</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/post/2023/helloworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 09:44:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/post/2023/helloworld/</guid>
      
      <description>Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m K.Boopathi! 👋 About Me I&amp;rsquo;m a passionate programmer with an insatiable curiosity for exploring diverse technologies and leveraging them to create cutting-edge products. My journey in the realm of tech is driven by a fervent desire to learn and innovate.
What I Do My blog is a reflection of my love for web development, offering insightful content, tutorials, and invaluable resources. I&amp;rsquo;m dedicated to sharing my knowledge and experiences, empowering aspiring developers to embark on their own coding adventures.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB Performance Tuning Book Notes</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2023/mongodb-performance-tuning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 09:44:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2023/mongodb-performance-tuning/</guid>
      
      <description>MongoDB Architecture and Concepts if the write concern is set to “majority”, then the database will not complete the write operation until a majority of secondaries receive the write. We can also set the write concern to wait until all secondaries or a specific number of secondaries receive the write operation.
Oplog The primary node stores information about document changes in a collection within its local database called the Oplog. The primary will continuously attempt to apply these changes to secondary instances.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/excalidraw/art-2024-01-19-19.56.09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/excalidraw/art-2024-01-19-19.56.09/</guid>
      
      <description>==⚠ Switch to EXCALIDRAW VIEW in the MORE OPTIONS menu of this document. ⚠==
Text Elements %%
Drawing { &amp;#34;type&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;excalidraw&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;version&amp;#34;: 2, &amp;#34;source&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;https://github.com/zsviczian/obsidian-excalidraw-plugin/releases/tag/2.0.13&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;elements&amp;#34;: [ { &amp;#34;id&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;lbilyLsh&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;type&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;text&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;x&amp;#34;: -251, &amp;#34;y&amp;#34;: -134.0234375, &amp;#34;width&amp;#34;: 137.2798614501953, &amp;#34;height&amp;#34;: 25, &amp;#34;angle&amp;#34;: 0, &amp;#34;strokeColor&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;#1e1e1e&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;backgroundColor&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;transparent&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;fillStyle&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;solid&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;strokeWidth&amp;#34;: 2, &amp;#34;strokeStyle&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;solid&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;roughness&amp;#34;: 1, &amp;#34;opacity&amp;#34;: 100, &amp;#34;groupIds&amp;#34;: [], &amp;#34;frameId&amp;#34;: null, &amp;#34;roundness&amp;#34;: null, &amp;#34;seed&amp;#34;: 300057372, &amp;#34;version&amp;#34;: 2, &amp;#34;versionNonce&amp;#34;: 157007772, &amp;#34;isDeleted&amp;#34;: true, &amp;#34;boundElements&amp;#34;: null, &amp;#34;updated&amp;#34;: 1705674402817, &amp;#34;link&amp;#34;: null, &amp;#34;locked&amp;#34;: false, &amp;#34;text&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;CTRL+Shift+V&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;rawText&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;CTRL+Shift+V&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;fontSize&amp;#34;: 20, &amp;#34;fontFamily&amp;#34;: 1, &amp;#34;textAlign&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;left&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;verticalAlign&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;top&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;baseline&amp;#34;: 18, &amp;#34;containerId&amp;#34;: null, &amp;#34;originalText&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;CTRL+Shift+V&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;lineHeight&amp;#34;: 1.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/linux/</guid>
      
      <description>Linux Filesystem Getting Help Every command, application, or utility has a dedicated help file in Linux by typing --help in front of all linux cmd or we can refer Manual Pages with man man cmd
CMD whereis: locate bin file whereis filename which: Return current PATH var for the bin whihc node find: search for file name ,date of creation or modification, etc find path -type f -name filename Files and Directories CMD get from chatgpt Text Manipulation cat head tail nl sed more less Networks ifconfig (Changing Your IP Address.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/napkin-maths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/napkin-maths/</guid>
      
      <description>Base rate (monthly)
CPU : 10/core Memory: 1/GB SSD: 0.01/GB Disk: 0.01/GB Network: 0.01/GB Cloud storage s3: 0.01/GB Base rate perfromance
S Fermi decmposition
Refernece https://github.com/sirupsen/napkin-math
3X income -&amp;gt; take 3x your monthly income and invest that in a year example 40k -&amp;gt; 3*40 = 12000k need to invest in a year 5 day rule -&amp;gt; get some money for invest need to have emerency fund (need to cover 3 to 6 month) Health insurance </description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/react/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/notes/2024/react/</guid>
      
      <description>useState for one-time initializations
const [resource] = React.useState(() =&amp;gt; new Resource()) React clone element for component compositon
React Add the key automatically
React.Children.tojArray(someData.map(item=&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;{item.title}&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;) Do you need to calculate the state from a state or props you already have Do that in the component and not in useEffect
Do you update state in useEffect when a prop changes? Wrong !
Using useEffect to update state is wrong because the props are not a side effect.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Search</title>
      <link>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://programmerraja.github.io/blog/search/</guid>
      
      <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
